A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Staff Subject Files, Jon Funabiki FA1447
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Staff Subject Files, Jon Funabiki
1990-2007
Rockefeller Archive Center
Funabiki, Jon
Ford Foundation
FA1447
23.4 Cubic Feet 61 boxes - 59 letter document containers, 1 legal document container, and 1 [19"x15"] photo storage box
Biographical / Historical
Jon Funabiki joined the Ford Foundation in 1995. He served as Deputy Director of the Media, Arts, and Culture Unit within the Knowledge, Creativity and Freedom Program. While at the Ford Foundation, he prioritized promoting ethics, credibility and diversity in journalism, strengthening media criticism, and promoting freedom of expression.
Jon Funabiki is a graduate of San Francisco State University. Prior to joining the Foundation, he was founding director of San Francisco State University's Center for Integration and Improvement of Journalism. He also directed News Watch: A critical look at coverage of people of color and Project Zinger, an annual analysis of coverage of Asian Pacific Americans, sponsored by the Asian American Journalists Association. Funabiki is a former reporter and editor with The San Diego Union, where he specialized in US-Asia political and economic affairs.
Funabiki is an emeritus professor in journalism at San Francisco State University.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains Jon Funabiki's office files from the Media, Arts and Culture (MAC) Unit with the Knowledge, Creativity and Freedom (KCF) Program, including grant records, grant-related materials such as RGAs, reports, article clippings, handwritten notes, grantees annual reports, financial statements, correspondence, office files, and meeting materials.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2018 and 2019 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accessions 2018:039, 2019:117, and 2019:138.
Arrangement
This collection contains two series and two subseries:
Series 1. Media, Arts, and Culture Grant Materials, 1992-2007
Subseries 1: Media and Journalism, 1992-2007
Subseries 2: Arts and Culture, 2003-2006
Series 2: Media, Arts, and Culture (MAC) Administrative Office Files, Meetings, and Reports, 1990-2007
Ford Foundation; Arts; Journalism; Journalism education; Journalistic Ethics; Media
- Media, Arts, and Culture (MAC) Grant Materials, 1992-2007; 1
  - Media and Journalism, 1992-2007; 1
    - Canadian Journalists for Free Expression RGA, 2001 October 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Grant No.: 0980-0149-2; 2 years and $170,000
    - Associated Press Managing Editors (APME) - Credibility Roundtables Study, 2004 August 16 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Evaluation of the Associated Press Managing Editors (APME) Credibility Roundtables Project - Executive Summary, 2004 June (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Associated Press Managing Editors (APME) - National Credibility Roundtables press materials, correspondence, and grant information, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Grant No.: 100014342
    - Associated Press Managing Editors (APME) - Rock Hill CD, undated; Optical Disk (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
    - Associated Press Managing Editors (APME) - National Credibility Roundtables, Speaking Out About Credibility, Toolkit for Speeches and Workshops, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Associated Press Managing Editors (APME) - National Credibility Roundtables, Speaking Out About Credibility, Toolkit, Credibility Roundtables Video Clips - DVD, undated; DVD (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Associated Press Managing Editor (APME) Association - National Credibility Roundtables, 2000-2005 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Grant Nos. 100014344, 100014343, 100014342, 100014341; $325,000 - correspondence, RGAs, proposals
    - Associated Press Managing Editor (APME) - National Credibility Roundtables Correspondence, RGAs, Press Materials, and Program Summaries (3 folders), 2003-2006 (Box 1, Folder 7-8, Box 2, Folder 9)
      Grant Nos. 100014344, 100024344, 100014343, 100014342,
    - Center for Investigative Reporting - Grant Materials, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Grant No.: 101014852 and RGA - grant proposal materials for "Banished," a documentary film on the history and legacy of forced expulsions of African Americand from their communities, and to seed other social justice journalism ventures; Grant No.: 101014851 and RGA - Supplementary support to create a team of journalists focused on issues of the misuse of power and secrecy
    - Center for Investigative Reporting - Grant Correspondence, 2005-2006 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Grant No.: 101014852 correspondence - grant proposal materials for "Banished," a documentary film on the history and legacy of forced expulsions of African Americans from their communities, and to seed other social justice journalism ventures; Grant No.: 101014851 correspondence
    - Center for Investigative Reporting - Reports, 2001-2005 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Financial Statements and Supplementary Information for the Year Ended December 31, 2004; Biannual Report; Biannual Report 2001-2002; Financial Statements and Supplementary Information for the Year Ended December 21, 2003
    - Center for Investigative Reporting - Reveal DVD Sample Reel, undated; DVD (Box 2, Folder 12)
      The Lawless Sea - FRONTLINE/World; Reasonable Doubt - CNN Presents; Peter Jennings Reporting: No Place to Hide - ABC
    - Center for Investigative Reporting - Banished and No Place to Hide, 2003-2005 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Memo; Banished: The Hidden History of How Whites Drove Blacks Out of Town in America - Proposal Summary, About the Producers: CIR and Two Tone Productions, Banished: The Investigation and its Media Components, Making an Impact: Educational Outreach and Publicity, Evaluation, Status of Project and Funding, Key People and Organizations, Budgets, Appendices; Correspondence; Notes from the opening of "No Place to Hide"; Investigating Injustice: Reporting to Reveal Abuses, Reach a Mass Audience and Inspire Change; Research Notes; Report for Grant No.: 101014851; press articles
    - Women's World Organization for Rights, Literature, and Development, Inc., 2003 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Grant No.: 10250629 - To facilitate a transition to Smith College and collaborations with Meridians magazine
    - Correspondence with Martin Abregu, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Correspondence regarding: research project on responsibility of the press in regard to subjects related to freedom of expression, human rights, and democracy in Chile's past; grant request for Work Cooperative La Vaca to develop Loudspeaker Project; Media Ownership Concentration in Latin America Executive Summary
    - Youth News Service Los Angeles Bureau - Grant Materials, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Grant No. 10102001 - 2 years beginning 9/1/01; For LA Youth, the nation's largest independent newspaper written by and for teens to implement its Teens, Crime, and the Juvenile Justice project
    - WNYC Foundation - "On the Media" Grant Materials (3 folders), 1999-2005 (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
      Grant No. 0990603 - Support for Production and Outreach Activities for the radio series "On the Media"
    - University of Washington (4 folders), 1999-2004 (Box 3, Folder 20-23)
      Grant No. 09900494 - Support for a study about news organizations and their relationships to communities
    - Community Development Associates - Grant Files (3 folders), 2002-2005 (Box 3, Folder 24-26)
      Grant Nos.: 10252011, 10451398 - inluding attachment files, correspondence, memos, The Ford Foundation New Directions/New Donors for the Arts Program Evaluation Final Report Executive Summary, Sustainability Project Monograph I: Mapping the Terrain Working Draft
    - Columbia Race Workshops, Sig Gissler - Grant Files (6 folders), 1998-2003 (Box 3, Folder 27-28, Box 4, Folder 29-32)
      Grant Nos. 9801255, 9800578 - Let's Do It Better Workshop on Journalism, Race and Ethnicity by Arlene Notoro Morgan; correspondence; The Authentic Voice: The Best Storytelling on Race and Ethnicity; Diversity Across the Curriculum: A Textbook Proposal; Journalism, Race and Ethnicity at The Columbia University Graduate School of Journalism Ford Foundation Renewal Proposal; Budget proposals; Appendix: Assessing the Quality of News Coverage of Ethnic and Minority Communities: Fordham Institute for Innovation in Socia Policy; Let's Do It Better! Workshop Agenda; "Covering the Global AIDS Crisis: New Approaches, New Stories" Conference Schedule; Tip Sheets; The 2001 "Let's Do It Better" Race Workshop Agenda; Let's Do It Better! Tips on Covering Racial and Ethnic Stories; Good Recruiting: No Straight Line to Success; Scholarships and Fellowships: Some Lessons; Creatng A Newsroom Diversity Committee; Time Out for Diversity and Accuracy; Racial Disparities in Health Coverage: Prescriptions for Change; Annual Report to the Ford Foundation; Interim Report to the Ford Foundation - 1999; press materials; Workshop follow-up materials
    - Columbia Race Workshops (2 folders), 1999-2003 (Box 4, Folder 33-34)
      Correspondence; Statement by Columbia University President Lee C. Bollinger; Press Materials; Photographers; Let's Do It Better! Growing Your Content; The Sixth Annual Let's Do It Better! Workshops on Journalism, Race and Ethnicity June 10-12, 2004 - A Compilation of Award-winning Print Work; Let's Do It Better - The Columbia Workshop on Journalism, Race, and Ethnicity - Selections from Honored Newspapers 1999 and 2000 booklets
    - Columbia Journalism Review (CJR) (3 folders), 1999-2005 (Box 4, Folder 35, Box 5, Folder 36-37)
      Grant No.: 9601351 - Correspondence; Program Action materials; proposal; CJR Business Plan; Biography of David Laventhol; Press releases; Appendix A - Columbia Journalism Review: Findings, Recommendations, and Goals Draft; Appendix B - Four Decades of the Columbia Journalism Review; Appendix C - Memos and materials relating to the Graduate School of Journalism; RGAs; Issues of the Columbia Journalism Review 2002-2005
    - Public Radio Studies, 2001-2004 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - San Francisco Site Visit, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 39)
      Institute for Justice and Journalism, Center for Investigative Reporting, New California Media, ZEUM at Yerba Buena Gardens
    - Diane Wong (Consultant) - Reframing the Immigration Debate Executive Summary, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Freedom of Expression Meeting ("Stone Soup"), New York (3 folders), 2004 March 5 (Box 5, Folder 41-43)
      United Nation's World Summit on the Information Society (WSIS) summary memo; Reflections on Humanitarian Action: Principles, Ethics and Contradiction; Brazil - Media - Office Pool; update memo; Summary Report - Ford International Roundtable on Journalism and Freedom of Expression; Freedom of Expression and Freedom of the Media; Use and Abuse of Media in Vulnerable Societies; A Needs Assessment for Media Development in Selected Countries in Francophone West Africa, with Recommendations for Follow-Up; International Donors Policy Forum on Media Development Draft 2; Correspondence; Memo - the case for a global and cross-programmatic free expression initiative within the Ford Foundation; Ford Foundation Freedom of Expression Working Group History and Overview of Activities 1999-2004; correspondence; A Civil Society Perspective on the World Summit on the Information Society, Steve Buckley March 2004; Expanding the Definition and the Constituency Working for Freedom of Expression; Summary Report: Ford International Roundtable on Journalism and Freedom of Expression; Statement on the Right to Communicate by Article 19 Global Campaign for Free Expression
    - Indiana University, Kinsey Institute and School of Journalism Grant Proposal - Barbara Klugman, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 44)
      Includes Media Action Plan (MAP) on HIV/AIDS and Gender Newsroom Policies
    - Amherst College - Replenishing Democracy Summer Institute, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 45)
      Includes schedule and budget report
    - Committee to Protect Journalists and the International Freedom of Expression Exchange, 2001-2005 (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Radio and Television News Directors Foundation (RTNDF) - Journalism Ethics and Integrity Project (4 folders), 2003-2005 (Box 6, Folder 47-50)
      Grant Nos: 098001267 and 097001344 - RGAs; RTNDA Communicator Magazine October 2005; Journalism Ethics and Integrity Project Final Report; Meeting Agendas; Financial Statements; Grant Attachments; Grant Report October 2000-2001; News Decision-Making Workshop
    - Pacific News Service - New California Media/Bay Area Institute (4 folders), 2004-2006 (Box 6, Folder 51, Box 7, Folder 52-54)
      Grant No.: 10500715, 09801125, 10151339 - RGAs; Business Plan Outline; correspondence; budget proposal; Grant Status Report; Final Narrative Report 10151339; First National EXPO of Ethnic and Youth Media program and drafts; Presentation to the Ford Foundation - 2004; The First National Ethnic Media Awards; Public Opinion Survey of Immigrants from Asia, The Middle East and Latin America on the War with Iraq and its Aftermath; Site Visits Memos; California Poll of Asian Americans on the Tsunami Executive Summary; notes; press materials
    - San Francisco State University Foundation - Center for the Integration and Improvement of Journalism (CIJI) (4 folders), 2001-2005 (Box 7, Folder 55-58)
      News Watch project - Grant No.: 09801124; 09600113 - correspondence; RGAs; newsletters; pamphlets; Center for Integration and Improvement of Journalism, October 2004; press materials
    - Pacifica Foundation (2 folders), 2004 (Box 8, Folder 59-60)
      Pacific Radio Archives - Grant proposal
    - San Jose State University - Grade the News (formerly Stanford University) (2 folders), 2002-2005 (Box 8, Folder 61-62)
      Grant 10251779, 20020342; RGA; proposal; press materials; report; correspondence
    - National Association of Black Journalists (NABJ) (3 folders), 1994-2005 (Box 8, Folder 63-65)
      Grant Nos: 95500453; 96001238; 9701349 - RGA; final reports; correspondence; press materials; Voices of Anger Cries of Concern: Some NABJ Views of the Retention Problem - and Some Solutions; Report; Building Bridges: NABJ's Leadership and Communication Workshop
    - Native American Journalists Association and Native American Press Association (3 folders), 1997-2003 (Box 8, Folder 66, Box 9, Folder 67-68)
      9701373 - RGA; proposal; correspondence; newsletters; conference materials
    - National Newspaper Publishers Association (NNPA), 2001-2004 (Box 9, Folder 69)
      Grant No.: 10101475 - correspondence; grant updates; budget; NNPA NorthStar Investigative Series: Executive Summaries - Education Series, Mississippi Land Series, Pickering Series, Higher Education and Race Series
    - National Lesbian and Gay Journalists Association (NLGJA) (3 folders), 1995-2006 (Box 9, Folder 70-72)
      Grant No.: 10000690 - reports, correspondence, pamphlets, newsletters
    - National Association of Hispanic Journalists (NAHJ) (3 folders), 1995-2005 (Box 9, Folder 73, Box 10, Folder 74-75)
      Grant No.: 9701350 - reports; publications
    - The New England Foundation for the Arts (NEFA)/Roundtable Preview Forum (6 folders), 2002-2004 (Box 10, Folder 76-80, Box 11, Folder 81)
      Grant No.: 10200609; 10400917 - For Preview Forum to bring together citizens and journalists in local communities to discuss news media issues; grant action documents, correspondence, reports, pamphlets
    - Koahnic Broadcast Corporation (3 folders), 2004-2005 (Box 11, Folder 82-84)
      Grant No.: 10401137; 10251842; 9701096 - RGA; correspondence
    - University of Maryland Foundation (3 folders), 1998-2006 (Box 11, Folder 85-87)
      Support to American Journalism Review - Grant No. 9701344 - RGA; correspondence; newsletters; reports
    - Rebecca Leet Associates, 2003-2005 (Box 12, Folder 88)
      Grant No.: 10350938 - correspondence; reports; RGA
    - Lumiere Productions, Inc. - "Democracy on Deadline", 2002-2005 (Box 12, Folder 89-90)
      Grant No.: 10300810; 10200471 - RGA; correspondence; reports; proposal
    - Investors Circle Mission-Driven Media Finance Project (3 folders), 2004-2006 (Box 12, Folder 91-93)
      Grant No.: 10351844 - RGAs; reports; correspondence; memos; The Double Bottom Line (DBL) Media Industry: An Analysis of Investment Opportunities Working Draft, October 2004; 2004 National Conference and Venture Fair materials; presentations; Mission-Related Investing: Strategies for Philanthropic Institutions May 2001
    - International Women's Media Foundation (2 folders), 1996-2006 (Box 12, Folder 94-95)
      Grant No.: 10250921; 100050242; RGAs; correspondence; reports; newsletters; notes
    - Maynard Institute (5 folders), 1993-2005 (Box 13, Folder 96-100)
      Grant No.: 09700447; 10051832; 9500257 - newsletter - The Maynard Journal; RGA; correspondence; Reports; proposal; Reality Checks Content Analysis Report, The Philadelphia Inquirer; budget reports; Seeing Ourselves and Our Communities Whole
    - Internews Network, 2005 (Box 13, Folder 101)
    - Mariano Aguirre - Institute for War and Peace Reporting, 2004-2005 (Box 13, Folder 102)
      Grant No.: 10451053 - correspondence; project proposal
    - TCC Group, Inc. - Challenge Fund for Journalism (5 folders), 2002-2006 (Box 14, Folder 103-107)
      Grant No.: 10201625
    - Unity: Journalists of Color (6 folders), 1995-2005 (Box 14, Folder 108, Box 15, Folder 109-113)
      Grant No.: 09701347 - Atlanta Unity '94 Convention, Inc.
    - University of Southern California - Online Journalism Review (4 folders), 2000-2006 (Box 15, Folder 114-116, Box 16, Folder 117)
      Grant No.: 10000390
    - University of Southern California - Institute for Justice & Journalism (6 folders), 2001-2008 (Box 16, Folder 118-123)
      Grant No. 1000-1447 - proposal, correspondence, RGAs, drafts of papers and reports, Strategic Plan 2005-2008
    - Fairness and Accuracy in Reporting Inc. (FAIR) (3 folders), 1997-2005 (Box 17, Folder 124-126)
      Grant No. 970-1345; 10550484
    - Independent Press Association Loan Fund PRI (3 folders), 2003-2005 (Box 17, Folder 127-129)
      Grant No. 10101483
    - Foundation-Administered Project (FAP), 2001-2003 (Box 17, Folder 130)
      Grant No.: 10190020
    - Foundation-Administered Project (FAP), 1998 (Box 17, Folder 131)
      Grant No.: 09890025
    - Funabiki Chronological File - Co-Responsible Program Officer (RPO), Recommended Grant Actions (RGA) and Delegated-Authority Grants (DAG) (3 folders), 1999-2003 (Box 17, Folder 132, Box 18, Folder 133-134)
      List of grantees: Cultural Co-operation; Diaspora Music Village; Women's Leadership Fund; Arab Press Freedom Watch; American Civil Liberties Union Foundation, Inc.; Bay Area Institute; Black Filmmakers Foundation; Youth Law Center; Bay Area Institute; The Committee to Protect Journalists, Inc; Crimes of War Education Project; Canadian Journalists for Free Expression; Center Theatre Group of Los Angeles; Duke University; Leslie Harris and Associates; Media Rights Agenda; New America Foundation
    - Communication Network, 2000-2004 (Box 18, Folder 135)
      Grant No.: 10351884
    - Community Renewal Society (4 folders), 2001-2006 (Box 18, Folder 136-139)
      Grant No: 10101488
    - Internews Network, 2005-2007 (Box 18, Folder 140)
    - Independent Press Association (IPA)(4 folders), 2003-2005 (Box 18, Folder 141, Box 19, Folder 142-144)
      Grant No.: 10101483
    - Highlander Pictures, Ltd. - When Muppets Dream of Peace, 2003-2006 (Box 19, Folder 145)
      Grant Nos: 10550296; 10200838
    - University of Georgia - Peabody Seminar, 2003-2005 (Box 19, Folder 146)
      Grant No. 10350499
    - Native American Media - National Indian Telecommunications Institute, Native American Public Broadcasting Consortium, Inc., Smithsonian Institution, Nihewan Foundation (3 folders), 1998-2002 (Box 19, Folder 147-149)
    - The Aspen Institute, Inc. (4 folders), 2004-2005 (Box 19, Folder 150, Box 20, Folder 151-153)
      Grant No. 10301831
    - The Aspen Institute, Inc. - Diversity Roundtables (3 folders), 1996-2001 (Box 20, Folder 154-156)
      Grant No.: 960-0698; 9700937; 970093
    - The Aspen Institute, Inc. - Stone Soup (4 folders), 2003-2004 (Box 20, Folder 157, Box 21, Folder 158-160)
      Grant No.: 9900721
    - Asian American Journalists Association (5 folders), 1997-2004 (Box 21, Folder 161-163, Box 22, Folder 164-165)
      Grant No: 9701347; 9701352; 9701349; 9701350; 9701373; 9301532; 9501240
    - American Documentary Active Voice (2 folders), 2003-2005 (Box 22, Folder 166-167)
    - Arizona State University Foundation, 2003-2006 (Box 22, Folder 168)
      Grant No.: 10551217
    - University of Missouri (8 folders), 1996-2001 (Box 22, Folder 169-172, Box 23, Folder 173-176)
      Grant No: 9701094, 9600699,
    - National Video Resources, 1998 (Box 23, Folder 177)
      Grant No.: 9750445
    - Native American Public Telecommunications, 1998-2000 (Box 23, Folder 178)
      Grant No. 09801525 - National Indian Telecommunications Institute, Native American Public Broadcasting Consortium, Inc., Smithsonian Institution, Nihewan Foundation
    - New Directions for News, 1997-2000 (Box 23, Folder 179)
      Grant No.: 09900718, 9701093
    - New York University - Framing Others: American Newspapers and the Coverage of Non-Christian Religion (2 folders), 1998-2000 (Box 23, Folder 180-181)
      Grant No.: 09800957
    - Progressive, Inc. - "Voices of Diversity" (3 folders), 1996-1999 (Box 24, Folder 182-184)
      Grant No.: 9600476
    - Progressive, Inc. - The Progressive Media Project (2 folders), 1999-2000 (Box 24, Folder 186-187)
      Grant No. 09800518
    - Radio and Television News Directors (3 folders), 1999-2000 (Box 24, Folder 188-190)
      Grant No.: 9801267
    - San Francisco State University (SFSU) Foundation and Center for Integration and Improvement of Journalism (CIIJ), 1995-1998 (Box 24, Folder 191)
      Grant No.: 9551400
    - San Francisco State University (SFSU) Foundation - Center for Integration and Improvement of Journalism (2 folders), 1994-1996 (Box 25, Folder 192-193)
      Grant No.: 9300876
    - The Working Group - Not In Our Town, 1998-2000 (Box 25, Folder 194)
      Grant No.: 9900412, 9700444
    - The Working Group - Not In Our Town II (3 folders), 1995-1999 (Box 25, Folder 195-197)
    - Nihewan Foundation, 1998-2000 (Box 25, Folder 198)
    - Poynter Institute for Media Studies, 1996-1997 (Box 25, Folder 199)
      Grant No. 9601132
    - Tides Center (4 folders), 1997-2001 (Box 25, Folder 200-201, Box 26, Folder 202-203)
      Grant No.: 9700939; 98001148
    - The Trustees of the University of Pennsylvania - RACETALK (5 folders), 1993-1999 (Box 26, Folder 204-208)
      Grant No. 9501246; 9500994
    - Africa News Service (2 folders), 1996-2002 (Box 26, Folder 209-210)
      Grant Nos: 9601315, 9601316, 9801279
    - Atlanta Unity '94 Convention, 1994-2000 (Box 26, Folder 211)
      Grant No.: 9400766, 9250776
    - Atlanta Unity '94 Convention, 1995 (Box 27, Folder 212)
      Grant No.: 9550869